翻译，压制：旋火
视频来源：youtu.be/U1j8ldnZ-gM
原视频发布日期：20191105
欢迎来到Rocket Lab 1号发射综合体(LC 1)
Welcome to Rocket Lab Launch Complex One.
这是Rocket Lab用于发射电子火箭的两个发射场之一
This is one of two Rocket Lab launch sites for the Electron launch vehicle.
注：2019年电子火箭于LC1发射6次
它建于2016年 每年这里可以支持超过120次发射
It was built in 2016 and we can support up to 120 launches here per year
LC1坐落于壮丽的新西兰东海岸的玛希亚半岛
Launch Complex One is located on the stunning Mahia Peninsula on New Zealand's East Coast
较少的海上交通和较大范围的轨道发射倾角
limited errand marine traffic and a wide range of orbital inclinations
从39度倾角到太阳同步轨道
from 39 degrees all the way up to Sun synchronous
使得这个发射场比世界上任何别的发射场更适合高频率发射
make this the best spot in the world for launching more frequently than anywhere else on the planet.
这里是LC1的载具仓库
We're standing inside the vehicle hangar today at Launch Complex One.
任务控制&装配总监
这是电子入轨前的最后一站
This is the last stop for Electron before orbit.
在发射活动的高峰期 我们大约有40到50人在这里进行发射准备工作
At the peak of launch operations, we have around 40 to 50 people here to support launch.
电子运载火箭的各个部件
The individual components of the Electron launch vehicle
在Rocket Lab的不同设施中进行组装并测试
are assembled and tested at different facilities at Rocket Lab
包括来自亨廷顿海滩的工厂3D打印的卢瑟福引擎
that includes the 3d printed Rutherford engines which come from our Huntington Beach facility
也有部分航电设备零部件
as well as some avionics components
然后将其运到奥克兰生产联合体
which are then shipped down to our Auckland Production Complex
在那里 会检查这些部件 之后把它们发去进行最后的综合测试
where they are inspected and sent out for final integrated testing.
一旦引擎完成了综合测试
Once the engines complete their integrated testing
就把它们带回奥克兰 并组装到火箭分级上
they're brought back to Auckland where they're integrated into the launch vehicle stages themselves
然后把这些分级都运到LC 1来进行最终测试和组装
and then those stages are shipped out to LC 1 for final tests and assembly.
这里是LC 1的无尘室
We're inside the cleanroom at Launch Complex One.
在这里 卫星被整合到kick stage上面的有效载荷板上
This is where the satellite gets integrated to the payload plate which is mounted on the kick stage
然后将有效载荷放入整流罩 这个过程被称为封装
and then the payload gets put into the fairing and a process called encapsulation.
在这个无尘室里 这也人们最后一次用手接触卫星
In this cleanroom this is the last time human hands will touch the satellites
在这之后就是抛整流罩以及卫星被部署到太空当中了
before the fairing opens up and they're deployed in space.
在无尘室里面 我们处理有效载荷
Inside the cleanroom we process the payloads
然后对眼前这个kick stage的电子和机械部件进行最终的组装
and then perform final electrical and mechanical mate to our kick stage which you see in front of me.
在封装期间 有效载荷和kick stage已经进行了电子和机械层面的组装
During an encapsulation the payload is already mechanically and electrically made it to the kick stage.
也就是这时 我们完成了kick stage和有效载荷的组装
At that point we break over the entire kick stage and payload assembly.
从这扇门里推出整流罩
We roll the fairing in from the doors
然后精确地将整流罩从kick stage和有效载荷上方推过来
and then we precision roll the fairing over the top of the kick stage plus the payload.
将其组装之后 就可以准备装到火箭上了
Then we perform a final mate and it's ready to be mounted to the launch vehicle itself.
LC 1有两个无尘室 所以我们可以同时处理两个有效载荷
LC 1 has two clean rooms so we can dual process two payloads at the same time.
在这个无尘室外面 我们有一个专门的客户区域
Just outside of this cleanroom we have a dedicated customer area.
这样 客户就可以坐着观看他们的载荷安装的过程
So customers can sit and observe the payload integration process
而不需要受到这个特殊无尘室的束缚了
without being bound up in this special clean facility.
这里是LC1的业务端
Welcome to the business end of Launch Complex One.
这是电子的发射平台 它的所有的动作发生在发射当天
This is Electron's launch platform and it's where all the action happens on launch day.
这个定制的发射塔架重达65吨
65 tons of steel go into this custom design launch mount and strong back.
在发射前数小时时间内 电子火箭被从载具仓库中水平推出
In the hours before liftoff, Electron has rolled out of the vehicle hanger horizontally.
然后机械臂抓紧火箭 并把它举起到待发射的垂直状态
Then the strong back secures on to the rocket and lifts it vertical ready for launch.
大约在发射前3小时 我们开始燃料加注作业
At about T-3h we begin fueling operations
给电子火箭加注高度精炼的煤油和液氧
to fill Electron with a highly refined kerosene and liquid oxygen
让卢瑟福引擎点火发射 准备入轨
for the Rutherford engines to burn through on their way to orbit.
人们往往关注着起飞那一刻的电子火箭
The focus tends to be on Electron at the moment of liftoff
但如果你仔细观察 你会发现一些同样工作的智慧的地面系统
but if you look closely you'll see some clever ground systems at work too.
在卢瑟福发动机 或者说电子火箭点火前约45秒
Around 45 seconds before the Rutherford engines and the Electron ignite,
喷水系统开始向火箭底部以每分钟上百升的速度进行喷洒
a water deluge systems start spraying hundreds of litres of water per minute at the base of the rocket.
水有助于抑制火箭起飞时(由发动机的运行所)产生的噪声
The water helps dampen the noise created by the roar of the rocket as it lifts off'
所以当你看到电子的起飞时的大片云雾时
so when you see the big cloud at the base of Electron during liftoff
那其实只是蒸汽产生的云
that's actually just a big cloud of steam created
此时 喷水系统喷出的水正在对付发动机火焰中的热量
when the heat from the engine flames meets the water from the deluge system.
今天行程的最后一站是远程控制
The last stop on today's tour is Range Control.
在发射当天 我身后的座位都会坐满了终端操作员
On launch day every seat behind me is filled with operators on console.
这里每个终端的操作员都在监控火箭 发射场和有效载荷
Each operator on console here is monitoring the vehicle, the pad and the payload
以确保它可以发射
to make sure that it's ready for launch
这包括天气和地面系统
that means everything from weather and ground systems
以及火箭上的推进和航电系统
all the way through to propulsion and avionics systems on the launch vehicle itself.
最后的倒计时来自奥克兰的任务控制中心
The final countdown comes from Mission Control in Auckland.
但是这里的团队在发射时更容易采取行动
But the team that spaced here is closest to the action during liftoff.
这里离发射场不到3km
At just under three kilometers from the pad
从这儿的窗户能看到很不错的风景
the team here gets a pretty spectacular view from the window right over there.
在几个月艰苦的工作之后 在这样一排能看到火箭发射的窗口前面庆祝是很不错的
After a lot of months of hard work it's a great way to celebrate with a front row view of the launch.
在未来的几个月里 你会看到我们将首次在美国领土上发射
In the coming months you'll see us embark on our maiden launch from US soil.
从Rocket Lab位于弗吉尼亚的瓦勒普斯岛的LC2发射
Launching from Rocket Lab Launch Complex Two on Wallops Island Virginia.
专为政府任务量身打造的LC2加强了我们的发射能力
Tailored specifically for government missions, LC2 complements our launch availability
这可以给美国政府客户提供更高频率和更灵活的发射服务
allowing even more frequency and flexibility for our US government customers.
我们无比自豪地把美国弗吉尼亚州称作是电子火箭的家
We're incredibly proud to call Virginia USA Electrons home.
注：到现在(2020.03.24)这里还没进行首次发射
我们迫不及待地期待着你观看(这个发射场)2020年初将进行的首次发射
and we can't wait for you to join us on our inaugural flight in early 2020.